GOVINDA Das: Shouldn't be able to Namaste, sir.
GOVINDA Das: Potato and other initiatives from New Orleans.
GOVINDA Das: Vaschut Deshtarani Jai Sri Krishna Chaitanya Nagar Shiv bhaiya bhaiya bhaiya bhaiya
GOVINDA Das: Hare Krishna, Hare Krishna, Hare Krishna
GOVINDA Das: I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
GOVINDA Das: Welcome, everybody, for, third session of our… Jyotish and Vastu Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: So, in the last two sessions, We discussed about Lagna, Rashi, Nawamsha Nakshatra
GOVINDA Das: And the basics of Vastu Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: So today, Like, again, to repeat… Lagna is your ego.
GOVINDA Das: Rashi is your mind.
GOVINDA Das: Nakshatra is a specific space of your mind, just like if you have a house.
GOVINDA Das: in Mira Road, or South Bombay, or Bandra.
GOVINDA Das: But still, within Bandra also, there is a specific place.
GOVINDA Das: It becomes more specific.
GOVINDA Das: The beauty of Jyotish Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: It begins with concrete and becomes more and more abstract.
GOVINDA Das: There are many models, Which talk about personality traits.
GOVINDA Das: They do go deeper, but because they reference.
GOVINDA Das: The knowledge system is so limited.
GOVINDA Das: They do not get into more detailed aspect of personality.
GOVINDA Das: But Jyotish Shaktra, just like how the creation…
GOVINDA Das: In this world, even though there are similar twins, Right?
GOVINDA Das: There are similar twins, they have absolutely same bodily features.
GOVINDA Das: But you'll still see there is a distinction and difference between one
GOVINDA Das: Brother to other twin brother, or one sister to other twin sister.
GOVINDA Das: The uniqueness of creation, it is marvelous.
GOVINDA Das: It is easier to create same model, you know, same Mercedes car, same model, thousands of them.
GOVINDA Das: But Prakriti, the creation, has the power to create everyone uniquely, even from the physical perspective.
GOVINDA Das: What to speak of the mental and emotional perspective there for astrology?
GOVINDA Das: Has to, by the very logic of diversity of the creation.
GOVINDA Das: has to make specific only connected to that particular person. As I said, it begins with commonality.
GOVINDA Das: About grouping, okay, you are Dhanu Lagana, that means there are some common trends.
GOVINDA Das: Within the new… When there is a particular nakshatra, that permutation and combination changes.
GOVINDA Das: And within that particular nakshatra, how the planets are situated.
GOVINDA Das: So it is not complex, it is profound.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, it is complex, but the purpose of complexity is to enhance the profoundity.
GOVINDA Das: Specify in regards to a person's personality.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, in the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna emphasizes so much on Swadharma.
GOVINDA Das: Because Swadharma… The will of God is as good as the will of that living entity.
GOVINDA Das: Non-different.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When somebody, people say sometime, oh, I don't know what is God's will. God's will is nothing.
GOVINDA Das: But…
GOVINDA Das: Finding your own traits and acting according to your traits, keeping dharma in the center, that itself is a God's will.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: Can you?
GOVINDA Das: Gordon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, slide.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: So… Can you go to the next one?
GOVINDA Das: We did discuss about Dasha.
GOVINDA Das: Like, Dasha… is the When somebody is born, according to their nakshatra, If somebody has… a nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: And then Nakshatra Swami is the beginning dasha of that particular person.
GOVINDA Das: If somebody has a Murgashira Nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: Then, the master, the Swamiya Murgachar Nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: I think Mars, so Mars is the beginning, the Shah.
GOVINDA Das: If somebody has the nakshatra connected to Guru, that is the beginning of their dasha. That means they are more influenced by that particular planet, because he is the master of that particular nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: Somebody else does Shatabeshana, etc.
GOVINDA Das: The master of that sattapishnakshatra is Rahu. So they begin with their Rahu dasha.
GOVINDA Das: Right, so please understand your nakshatra swami.
GOVINDA Das: Is the beginning of your dasha.
GOVINDA Das: And then the Shah keep on moving one after another and therefore Lord Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: Lived for 125 years.
GOVINDA Das: And the entire dasha, when you calculate one after other, it is 120 years.
GOVINDA Das: So, Krishna completed the cycle of Dasha.
GOVINDA Das: He chose when to be born.
GOVINDA Das: Rohini nakshatra kar ka lagna
GOVINDA Das: Right, Lord Ramachandra also, if you study the Srimad Bhagavatam, if you study the Srimad Ramayana of Valmiki Maharshi, one has to understand even the avataras.
GOVINDA Das: They are beyond all the planetary position.
GOVINDA Das: They make planet his Krishna Graha.
GOVINDA Das: Right, but because they come to this world, they respect the laws of this world and choose something as auspicious as possible.
GOVINDA Das: They are not bound by that, but they are teaching a lesson to us.
GOVINDA Das: Right, so dasha is, again, your nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: Means beginning of your dasha, the swami of that nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: And what is Gochar? Gochar is…
GOVINDA Das: When we are born on a particular time.
GOVINDA Das: That is Lagna. All the planetary positions are already seen.
GOVINDA Das: Where is which nakshatra sitting? Which planets are sitting? What is the Lagna? Is it Dhanu Lagna? Is it Tula Lagna? Is it Rishabha Lagna?
GOVINDA Das: So, the Jyotish Shastragya makes our chart based upon our birth. That is called as Lagna chart.
GOVINDA Das: But what is the transit ghoster, because the planets keep moving.
GOVINDA Das: Different planets move according to different time.
GOVINDA Das: Jupiter, Shani, They take long time to move from one zodiac sign to other zodiac sign.
GOVINDA Das: The moon planet, for that matter, moves, he takes only 2 and a half days.
GOVINDA Das: From moving to one zodiac sign to other zodiac sign.
GOVINDA Das: So there is a continuous movement. One is the constant, our birth chart, and there is a continuous movement. And that continuous movement transit also impacts our chart.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When that impacts our chart, If today… My Shania Rahu.
GOVINDA Das: Are sitting in my Lagna, in the first house.
GOVINDA Das: even though one may have best position, best Lagna chart, but today, for some time, depending upon which planet is sitting, one year, two years, that Gochara also impacts our
GOVINDA Das: Situation today. Is it permanent? No.
GOVINDA Das: It is transit.
GOVINDA Das: Right, it is there for some time, it creates certain impact, positive, negative, and again it moves on.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the chart is the photograph.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, Gochar is the light still falling on it on a particular planet.
GOVINDA Das: Karan, you want to add something?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Nobody's here. Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: One of the most misunderstood concept of Jyotish Shastra is Sadesati.
GOVINDA Das: The PPT mentions there is nothing occult in the number.
GOVINDA Das: The word sadeshati is not a bad word.
GOVINDA Das: Right, in the, in the, in the Varnashram system, when we say, oh.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he's Shudra, he's a Brahmana.
GOVINDA Das: She's a Kshatriya He is Vaishya.
GOVINDA Das: If you study carefully, the word shudra is not a bad word.
GOVINDA Das: It may have a bad connotation because of the social system.
GOVINDA Das: Recently, one Sanskrit scholar, when he was doing Upanayan Samskara.
GOVINDA Das: He was quoting from the Nirukta. Nirukta is the foundational idea or the etymology of the word.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime you use any word for anything, but this is Nirukta, etymologically explaining the word.
GOVINDA Das: So, sometime, many words have many definition.
GOVINDA Das: So one word shudra means what one know melts.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, such people are always considerate in regards to serving others.
GOVINDA Das: They are driven by emotions.
GOVINDA Das: When they're driven by emotions, they are available to serve others.
GOVINDA Das: Right? That is the clear. And again, the beauty of Jyotish Shastra, if somebody says, oh, India has so much of caste system, wish people knew some aspect of Jyotish Shastra. In the Jyotish Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Even though you may be born in a Brahmin family.
GOVINDA Das: Or you may be born in a so-called Shudra family that is Jati.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, it has an impact.
GOVINDA Das: We discussed that on the second day, Guna, Karma, and Jati.
GOVINDA Das: But in astrology, in Jyothi Shastra, based upon your nakshatra, your varana also decided, your mental varana is decided.
GOVINDA Das: Somebody may have the powerful background of being born in a royal family, but if their nakshatra is connected to
GOVINDA Das: particular nakshatra, then even nakshatradar divided. Shudra nakshatra, Kshatriya nakshatra, Brahman nakshatra, and then Vaishna nakshatra. What does it indicate? It does not indicate your birth. It indicates your mental impact.
GOVINDA Das: No? Your Lagna could be Brahmana, Dhanu.
GOVINDA Das: Your Rashi could be somebody else, but your Nakshatra defines what Varani belong to you, so therefore it is not black and white.
GOVINDA Das: You know, if you have the app, if you go and see what is my Varuna, you'll be humbled.
GOVINDA Das: Or you'll feel, oh, good, no problem, even though I'm born in such a particular family, but I have the disposition of Brahmanical nature.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, I am born in this particular family, I have the disposition of servitorship.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So, therefore, there are so much of misunderstanding in regards to Varuna. Similarly, in regards to Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: There is a great misunderstanding amongst the people.
GOVINDA Das: In 2014 or 2015, this was told to us by our teacher, Astrologer, when he was teaching us.
GOVINDA Das: when the Prime Minister He became the prime minister within 1 or 2 years. He made it Chowkidar.
GOVINDA Das: You must have seen that chunky dial.
GOVINDA Das: And this devotee astrologer was telling us.
GOVINDA Das: Because Modiji was going through Sade Sati, he became Prime Minister during Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: And when you become such a big personality.
GOVINDA Das: During that period, the nature of Shani is connected to Sade Sati. We will discuss how it happens, but I'll give some philosophical background.
GOVINDA Das: The nature of Shani is Shani is the socialist by nature.
GOVINDA Das: Shani… Naturally gives attention to underprivileged people.
GOVINDA Das: Gives attention to elderly people. Gives attention to disabled persons.
GOVINDA Das: Gives attention to elderly people.
GOVINDA Das: Gives attention to those who have less resources.
GOVINDA Das: gives attention to, you know, going very slowly. Why does he do that? Because Shani himself
GOVINDA Das: His leg broken by his own father, Surya Dev.
GOVINDA Das: So, Shani goes very slow. It is… you want to take it historically, or you want to take symbolically, or you want to take astrologically, it doesn't matter. Today, we are discussing Jyotish Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, he walks slow and is extremely sensitive to those people who are underprivileged.
GOVINDA Das: And what does the prime minister, chief minister, mayor, CEO, or the king represents? They represent Surya Planet, Adhikar.
GOVINDA Das: So, when the Surya and Shani…
GOVINDA Das: They face each other, there is a conflict of ruling.
GOVINDA Das: And challenging the concept of ruling.
GOVINDA Das: Shani challenges the sun.
GOVINDA Das: He doesn't like authoritarian people.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, he could create certain trouble and challenges.
GOVINDA Das: But if your disposition, even if you're the king, even if you're the CEO, even if you're the great master, but if somebody takes the lower disposition.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, you have a position of the king, but if you choose the disposition of Sevak.
GOVINDA Das: What does it do? He says, okay, then you work.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, because of the personality of the Prime Minister workaholic, it simply benefited him.
GOVINDA Das: immensely by their disposition, And there was another leader, I have not confirmed it.
GOVINDA Das: But again, this Jyotish Shastra get told.
GOVINDA Das: There's another leader… You know, entitled in mindset.
GOVINDA Das: No, privileged in upbringing.
GOVINDA Das: Even he was going through Sade Sati, but the mindset of privileged.
GOVINDA Das: Mindset of being very special.
GOVINDA Das: What did Shani do? Shani destroyed, repeatedly making this person lose election after election, election after election. And on top of that, if he knew a little astrology, he could have not made this statement.
GOVINDA Das: Shani cannot stand that.
GOVINDA Das: If you are undermining somebody wants to have the disposition of and you call that even though if he has some element of wrong.
GOVINDA Das: But because you, having Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: Right? He was going through Sade Satya also. But if you make certain statement, rather than being humble, Shani flattens your ego.
GOVINDA Das: And how does he flatten your ego? He flattens your ego by repeatedly showing you that how you are failing.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, it is explained during sadhya sati. It is the best time to practice humility.
GOVINDA Das: If somebody is going through Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: And somebody does something wrong, simple wrong.
GOVINDA Das: And you try to fight them. If you're traveling in a car and somebody honks behind you, and if you're going through sadhi sati, it is not good to get out of the car and challenge them, fight them, debate with them.
GOVINDA Das: Saying, okay, it's my trouble, my problem.
GOVINDA Das: Let me not get out and move on. So Shani become very pleased.
GOVINDA Das: So, what is Sade Sati? As I said.
GOVINDA Das: There is Lagna. There is Rashi.
GOVINDA Das: And Sade Sati means… Shani travels two and a half years in each planet.
GOVINDA Das: When he travels in each planet, That Shani…
GOVINDA Das: When it comes one planet, that is moon.
GOVINDA Das: In one house, the house before the moon, you must have seen the 12 homes. Imagine moon in your birth chart is sitting in the 10 number. I'm giving you a number. Number 10 means Makara Rashi.
GOVINDA Das: And then that is your lagana.
GOVINDA Das: The Chandra of your Lagna is sitting in the number 10 because in the chart they talk number 10. Number 10 means Makar.
GOVINDA Das: And that Shani, the Gochar Shani, after traveling many years, eventually comes to the number 9 house.
GOVINDA Das: or number 9 sign that is Dhanu.
GOVINDA Das: So, what happened? Because Chandra… He's sitting in the 10th number.
GOVINDA Das: Shani, the gochar, the transit Shani has come in the 9th number, so that is the first phase of Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: Because it's very close to the moon, your mind starts.
GOVINDA Das: Activated. Positively, negatively.
GOVINDA Das: That is the first phase. He will stay there for 2 and a half years.
GOVINDA Das: Then, eventually, the transit Sunny will move into the 10th number, that is Makara, sitting in the same house.
GOVINDA Das: Shani is also there and Lagna, the Burthka Lagna is also there in the form of Chandra. So when Chandra and Shani are together sitting in the same house, Lagna's Chandra and Transit Shani, that is the second phase of your Sadhya Sati.
GOVINDA Das: And the third, after two and a half years, then that Shani moves to the number 11, Kumbharashi.
GOVINDA Das: So that is the last phase of Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: When that goes in the last phase, two and a half years, two and a half years, two and a half years. Sade sati means what? Sade means seven and a half.
GOVINDA Das: But that number itself, imagine, because we don't know, the number 7.5…
GOVINDA Das: is seen as something very inauspicious, but there is nothing inauspicious about it. We will see the
GOVINDA Das: Advantage and disadvantage of sadhisati to comfort everybody and do not give importance to it to such an extent.
GOVINDA Das: That one becomes suffering without any negative impact of sadhisati.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, it crosses your Lagana, not your Rashi. Saturn passes over the moon, the mind, the emotional nature.
GOVINDA Das: Felt inwardly long before it is seen outwardly. Yes, first we start experiencing in our own inner mind.
GOVINDA Das: Then it starts manifesting externally because whatever is there in the mind, eventually it becomes an external reality.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, what is the period giving us? The Shani Dasha, Sade Sati, not Shani Dasha. Shani Dasha is different from Sade Sati. There is Rahu Dasha, there is Shani Dasha, there is Guru Dasha, there is Mangal Dasha, we discussed that, but Sade Sati is different.
GOVINDA Das: What is the nature of Shani? Shani's nature is the planet of discipline.
GOVINDA Das: Shani is like playing a test match.
GOVINDA Das: Moon is like playing T20 match.
GOVINDA Das: Right, those who always played test match, when the T20 came, they said, what is this?
GOVINDA Das: You know, this is nonsense.
GOVINDA Das: Red… Therefore, one of the reasons why Sadasati impacts, because moon is extremely creative.
GOVINDA Das: Moon is extremely imaginative.
GOVINDA Das: Moon is extremely fast moving.
GOVINDA Das: Moon is based upon feeling, not fact.
GOVINDA Das: And Shani has no feeling other than fact.
GOVINDA Das: When fact and feeling contradict, Fast moving and slow moving contradict.
GOVINDA Das: Okay?
GOVINDA Das: Chandra being very party-feeling person, and Moon is feeling person, and Shani is acting person, slow and steady. The combination of the two, it is called as Vishya Yoga.
GOVINDA Das: Again, visha yoga, not necessarily bad.
GOVINDA Das: If somebody has Shani and Chandra together, it is called as yoga. The interesting part is
GOVINDA Das: Whether it is Vishya Yoga, whether it is Gajakeshara Yoga, or whether it is Raja Yoga.
GOVINDA Das: Each combination is called as yoga only, and yoga is not a bad word.
GOVINDA Das: Like our teacher was mentioning, when Shani and Chandra combined.
GOVINDA Das: You know, that means they were born with sadeshati. What does it do if you are able to reconcile between your fast-moving shani?
GOVINDA Das: Slow moving Shani and fast moving Chandra, you could be so creative at the same time, extremely practical.
GOVINDA Das: You are able to reconcile the most impactful opposites for your advantage.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When moon… And Mars are together. There is action.
GOVINDA Das: And there is refinance also. If we do not know, then they become contradictory to each other.
GOVINDA Das: If there is Shani and Surya, what does it do? Shani is slow. Shani is angry with authority.
GOVINDA Das: But if the authority himself becomes very submissive, very honest, very, very, very nicely disposed.
GOVINDA Das: Then Shani and Surya give better benefits also.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, the person is practicing life.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than feeling discouraged by certain particular planetary combination, if they use it properly, rather than becoming yoga, it becomes yoga.
GOVINDA Das: So what does it do? Greater discipline in work and in finances. You cannot, you cannot just throw your wealth.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot live a reckless life. Shani will beat you.
GOVINDA Das: Learning to distinguish what is essential from what is unnecessary.
GOVINDA Das: Shani helps one to understand want.
GOVINDA Das: And need.
GOVINDA Das: Chandra, I want. Shani, I need.
GOVINDA Das: Long-term career of financial stability built through sustained effort. As I said, Shani means playing test match.
GOVINDA Das: Tehmeh, Tehmeh, D Every drop makes it into ocean. Somebody is going to Sadesati.
GOVINDA Das: And they want to make a quick money through…
GOVINDA Das: Investments, especially the, you know, the… You know, the day-to-day trading…
GOVINDA Das: What does Shani do? Shani, because it's a planet, it's an influence. We are not saying that Shani will come and destroy you. The planetary influence, tomorrow we'll discuss that in the Shimad Bhakut M fifth canto, how each planet has its influence on the other planets also.
GOVINDA Das: Shukutegosham is speaking this.
GOVINDA Das: Right. So therefore, one is conscious and aware. What does it do? The financial stability built through sustained effort.
GOVINDA Das: Benefits them, they don't become.
GOVINDA Das: Harmed by stupid decisions, spiritual growth, humility, and deeper sense of responsibility.
GOVINDA Das: Shani certainly does that. If somebody has, imagine.
GOVINDA Das: You know, somebody's going through a lot of fun, And suddenly, they experience Adesati.
GOVINDA Das: Right, imagine in, in your Chandra Dasha or in your Suri Dasha or in your Shukra Dasha, suddenly Sadhya Tesatis comes, they feel life has completely gone upside down, topsy-turvy.
GOVINDA Das: Now there is nothing topsy turvy. It is there, but now you become a little sober. Next.
GOVINDA Das: Delays in the achieving of goals, it takes time.
GOVINDA Das: Financial pressure that requires careful budgeting. Again, discipline.
GOVINDA Das: Shani brings discipline. He does not bring
GOVINDA Das: Ill luck. He brings discipline. Increase responsibilities at work or within the family.
GOVINDA Das: Health concerns from stress or overwork if self-care is neglected.
GOVINDA Das: Feeling of loneliness, emotional heaviness or isolation because Shani by nature is not a party person.
GOVINDA Das: No, he doesn't get into party mode. He's a more of a recluse. So therefore those impact also do happen.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: One more before the slide. This before that.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, next.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, sure.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: Please, as we have mentioned here.
GOVINDA Das: If self-care is neglected, it does not say that illness comes.
GOVINDA Das: It says it comes if self care is neglected.
GOVINDA Das: So Sade Sati does not bring ill wealth, ill health, ill problem.
GOVINDA Das: Sade Sati only requests us to become sober.
GOVINDA Das: And thoughtful.
GOVINDA Das: Because that is the nature. The whole doctrine of the second phase of karma sits inside that clause.
GOVINDA Das: You know the the karmic cycle which is operating systematically and therefore the Bharti Sanskriti if you study carefully the Hindu scripture.
GOVINDA Das: Vaishnava scripture, whatever scripture one is reading, It is the…
GOVINDA Das: They talk about a responsibility over rights.
GOVINDA Das: Modern civilization focuses on rights over responsibility.
GOVINDA Das: When there are only rights and no responsibility, what does it do? It makes people go reckless.
GOVINDA Das: And once they go reckless, Right? Then they play the victim card when they have to face the consequences.
GOVINDA Das: But Sade Sati…
GOVINDA Das: It only enhances the understanding of Sanatana Dharma. If I'm responsible, then my rights are the natural consequences of my responsibility.
GOVINDA Das: Right, we were discussing… Very interesting point, one army officer said.
GOVINDA Das: Karma itself is a phala.
GOVINDA Das: So Shani does that. If you focus on karma, your action, your responsibility, that very responsibility itself becomes consequences.
GOVINDA Das: There is no different fruit. Your responsibility itself becomes your fruit.
GOVINDA Das: That that integrated understanding become much deeper and you find great pleasure in performing your work itself.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, the result will not come. Result will come, but that is not emphasized by a person who's self… one who's person who's doing his self-care. He focuses… she focuses on doing their duty diligently.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: Saturn is not magistrate handing down a sentence.
GOVINDA Das: Even in the modern world, When a judiciary punishes, judiciary does not execute.
GOVINDA Das: Execution is done by somebody else.
GOVINDA Das: They only declare the reality of what is going to happen to you.
GOVINDA Das: They do not implement. Similarly, Sade Sati Satan.
GOVINDA Das: Either… He is not a magistrate.
GOVINDA Das: He is not handing down sentence.
GOVINDA Das: Saturn is the stern teacher who slows you down.
GOVINDA Das: You know, those who are always jumping, dancing, what does he do? He slows them down. Delaying Saturn's method of instruction.
GOVINDA Das: In the Dharma Shastra, in the Mahabharat, There is a story of.
GOVINDA Das: Nahusha. Nahusha was an ancestor of the Pandavas.
GOVINDA Das: So, when he became the king.
GOVINDA Das: The king of the heavenly planets chasing away the original Indra.
GOVINDA Das: Purandara.
GOVINDA Das: And he said, I want Sachi.
GOVINDA Das: They said Sachi is not a position. She is a wife of particular Indra. It is totally offensive on your part to ask for her.
GOVINDA Das: But he was intoxicated by ego.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: And the Saptarishis.
GOVINDA Das: One of the rishi was Agastya.
GOVINDA Das: Right? And Agast Rishi… He has walking problem. He walks very slowly.
GOVINDA Das: When Nahusha, I'll come back to Augusta, when Nahusha insisted I want Tachi, Brahaspati is a guru.
GOVINDA Das: He came to Sachi Mata, that is Indra's wife, and he told about this.
GOVINDA Das: And if you don't worry, what we will do.
GOVINDA Das: Is that you tell him to come.
GOVINDA Das: On the palanquin carried by Saptarishis.
GOVINDA Das: Right? And this Nahosha was intoxicated with arrogance.
GOVINDA Das: When this news was brought to Nahusha, he invited all the Saptarishis.
GOVINDA Das: Very interesting, in the Bhagavatam, it is explained, the entire planetary position is like a shishumar, dolphin.
GOVINDA Das: Right? After all the planet and Nakshatra, there are Saptarishis.
GOVINDA Das: And if you have the connection to the Gotra Rishi.
GOVINDA Das: The power of the planet, it'll be there.
GOVINDA Das: But it will not harm so much.
GOVINDA Das: Right? He came, Brahaspati came, and he told, this is the demand of Sachi, Indra's wife.
GOVINDA Das: That you should be carried by a Saptarishis.
GOVINDA Das: And Nahusha… He was so intoxicated.
GOVINDA Das: He called all the seven rishis, you have to carry me.
GOVINDA Das: And they started carrying him on the palanquin.
GOVINDA Das: Rishis are humble.
GOVINDA Das: As he was going forward, Nahusha being very intoxicated, very eager, very excited.
GOVINDA Das: He saw Augusta Rishi was walking very slowly.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore he kicked Agastar Rishi calling Sarpa, Sarpa, Jandikaro, Jandikaro, do it fast.
GOVINDA Das: Right? And then Augusto cursed him to become snake.
GOVINDA Das: The… the learning lesson here is.
GOVINDA Das: That when you force something beyond its stipulated time.
GOVINDA Das: If you're about to reach somewhere in 2 hours.
GOVINDA Das: You try to make it 1 hour, Shani does not like that.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he will not be happy with that.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, what does it do?
GOVINDA Das: Oh!
GOVINDA Das: What do you do? You basically respect the power of Sade Sati.
GOVINDA Das: The loneliness is the classroom emptying so that you can hear yourself.
GOVINDA Das: Right? There are nobody you are sitting alone.
GOVINDA Das: so that you can focus on hearing your own self. That is what sadhisati does, or sometimes shanidasha, depending on where it is sitting.
GOVINDA Das: Even Sade Sati also differs from one person Sade Sati to other person Sade Sati in the same time because somebody's.
GOVINDA Das: The moon may be sitting in the first house, according to the Lagna chart.
GOVINDA Das: And somebody's… Moon is sitting in the 10th.
GOVINDA Das: House.
GOVINDA Das: sitting in the… the…
GOVINDA Das: Same planet is the same, but the position is different. Home planets are different. So therefore, two will experience different kind of satyasati.
GOVINDA Das: Yep.
GOVINDA Das: Next.
GOVINDA Das: Have the last few years asked you for patience, for economy, for the shedding of what was never essential?
GOVINDA Das: You know, we can, we can, we can basically contemplate on this.
GOVINDA Das: Not that when it will, this will be over, but what is the reason teaching? What is the reason teaching me? And what I refuse to learn from it, agar drishti badal gayi, to drishya apnea badal jata hai.
GOVINDA Das: Karan, you want to add something?
GOVINDA Das: Foods.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oh, gotcha. I think so Perfect.
GOVINDA Das: We'll start now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yes, for sure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you, Bridget. So… Continuing from…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Where Prabhuji mentioned, like, your chart is basically the position or the photograph that was taken at your birth.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then there is Gochara and Dasha, which is the dynamic aspect of astrology. Similarly, in Vastu also, like we'll come to the slide, but just to continue from there, then Vastu also, the house you are living in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, you purchased it a few years ago, it's a rented house, it's probably there with you for years or decades. That's the stirrup part, or that's the… that's the static, or that's the… of course, static is not the right word, but that's the photograph that you are currently living in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But in Vastu also, there is a component which is called as Jivit Vastu. In the sense, what you do dynamically with the house, what you kind of do to kind of enhance the energies of the house, to enhance the positivity or the auspiciousness as the Shastras speak.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, that is the Jivit Vasu, so there's a Stirvasu, that is what you have, and probably you cannot change so easily, and there is a Jivit Vasu component, which is what you do, and that's, that's where the remedies part
Dr. Karan Mittal: which is nowadays quite famous or quite quite you know it's like the remedies part comes under the jivat vastu but that's just another component of the jivat vastu but what you do on a daily basis to the house whether it's you know lighting the hours whether it's the main door enhancement whether it's cleaning the house with salt Etc these are things also given in shastas to keep on you know
Dr. Karan Mittal: replenishing or regenerating the energies of the house, that comes in the Jivit Vastu.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So today, probably, as we go ahead, of course, I'll come to Namanji's question, then Shubhamne's question. Today, we'll cover those questions. But as we go ahead, we'll try to see how or where do these planets — we've already seen that your Chandra Rashi or the moon sign governs your mind, and your Levinarashi kind of governs.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How, how you, like, how the world perceives you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and also the nakshatra part, which is your signature, and the dasha, which is your time, like, the time that is currently happening in your life. We'll also see, like, all these
Dr. Karan Mittal: Four components that we have mentioned have a planet, so you will have a planet like that. Suppose your Rashi is Mithun Rashi or the Gemini, then the Lord of that is Buddha or Mercury.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If your Lagna is probably Neil, then the Lord is probably Jupiter, Guru. If your Dasha is Shani, or probably your Lakshatra Lord is Mars. So all these components have a planetary Lord.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That planetary Lord will try to see where does this, where we will see that, where does this planetary Lord come into Navasthu in the sense.
Dr. Karan Mittal: where are these planets located in the Vastu, and then we take it forward of how to analyze the Vastu, how to kind of start changing the Vastu, the Jivit component of the Vastu, and then probably bring the auspiciousness of these four planets that we have discussed, into our lives.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you already know your Vashis and Lagmas and Dashas, etc. So, it's always good now to kind of, you know, like, if you have a paper or a book, to write these four components, and then probably in a few, like, days, you'll already start remembering that, okay, this is my Vashi, this is my Lord.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, and which direction it corresponds to. So it will, it will become, like something that, that, that's there on your,
Dr. Karan Mittal: tongue. So, let's… let's move ahead, and let's try to see. So, these are the lords. Of course, I've… I've mentioned these in the handouts also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: these are the lords of different rashis, or different zodiacs. So if it's Amish, then it's Mars, probably Vishal, it's Venus, Gemini, it's Mercury, and so on. So you can just note the rashis, and note the lords of those rashis. So basically, these are the governing
Dr. Karan Mittal: the planets to your particular ashi. So, someone had asked this question, what's the difference between the Lord and the deity? So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Lord is basically the planet that rules that Rashi, or that Nakshatra. So, it can be out of the nine planets that we have studied. Any of these can be ruling,
Dr. Karan Mittal: a particular rashya nakshatra. Of course, Rahu and Ketu don't rule the rashis, they only rule nakshatras. Of course, there are some, some, some intricate details, but those are the lots, or rahadipati, we call it in Sanskrit.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And deities are basically the demigods or the presiding devatas of a particular rashi or of a particular nakshatra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So as I said last time, for Mergashira, it's probably Soma, that is Somadevata of Veda. He's the presiding deity of that particular nakshatra. So both are different. Both can be worshipped or chanted for, given dance for, to enhance the power or to enhance the auspiciousness of a particular rashi or a nakshatra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Dharana Tapa, and that will come when we start doing the remedies part of all these things, will come to the Dharana Tapa and Yogya Pond.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's about the rashis. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, so what I mentioned is, write down your Rashi Swami, the Lord of your Rashi, the Dhradipati.
Dr. Karan Mittal: write your Lagna Swami, the Lord of your Lagna, your Dasha Lord, the current Dasha you are in, and your Nakshatra Lord. So just write them down, and we'll see how we start using it in, from the Vastu perspective. So, last time we saw
Dr. Karan Mittal: how to find the center point of the house, and we kind of made a quadrilateral plan and tried to kind of find the intersections to find the center point of the house. And we also saw that, you know, you go to this point and put a compass over there, and trying to find where exactly the rent
Dr. Karan Mittal: Part of the compass or or the north is and.
Dr. Karan Mittal: From there, we kind of make this grid. Each zone is around 45 degrees, so from the line or the axis that joins the Brahmastana to the north.
Dr. Karan Mittal: 22.5 degrees to the left, 22.5 degrees to the right becomes the north zone. And then you just need to kind of use a protractor and make 45 degrees of angles each to finally find out the layout of the house. And then we also saw that you can locate what element or what activity
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is currently there in that particular area of the house, so I mentioned like in the northeast there's a bedroom, so the activity is basically sleeping or inertia or a thermos-based activity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the east, we have a toilet. In southeast, we have, again, a bedroom. So, just finding the layout and trying to kind of mark what activity or what possible room is there in that particular direction of the house. And then.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Someone asked if the house is not oriented.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, and the exact
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like in the exact right angle or the 90 degree kind of facing the top then it's at our level it's completely fine to work with the house that is tilted so like you're probably there's a tilt of approximately 19 degrees okay now just a very approximate tilt so I found out that okay so I went to the center of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I went to the center of the house, I kept a compass, and then I found out that the north is not
Dr. Karan Mittal: straight, and the north is kind of tilted by 19 degrees. So, no problem. I kind of made this line 22.5 degrees here, 22.5 degrees here, so this is the north zone, and then again, I went clockwise or anti-clockwise to make this grid.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, the tilt changes the orientation, but for us, just because we're working with 8 directions, it doesn't matter a lot. We just work as per where the compass points to the north, and then make the grid.
Dr. Karan Mittal: in the clockwise manner of all the directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I think in the first class that we saw, the master class which had happened a month ago, we saw that the Vastu comes… maybe you could refer that class if you want to go deeper into it. So, the Vastu Shastra, of course, it's considered an Upaveda. The Stapaktiveda is also considered an Upaveda.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But it also comes from, traditionally, from two darshanas, the Vaisheshik darshana of Indian philosophy and the Sankh
Dr. Karan Mittal: Where Dhik, that is Disha, is considered one of the Mahabhutas. So, apart from the 5 Mahabhutas, we call them 9 Dravyas, there are 4 Mudravyas, Man, Atma, Dhik, and Kala.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So one is basically the psychological part. Atma is the spiritual part. Vik is basically the directions or the space.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And Kala is basically the Jyotisha component or the time component of our universal creation as per Vaisheshi Shastra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So these are not… these are not shastras that were created later. The roots are found in Vedas, the roots are found in Adarshan shastras. It's just that Rishis meditated and brought up… brought out different Ganthas.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Eventually, as time passed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So when we get into Vastu, at our level, we'll see Vastu from five different perspectives. So all these perspectives, as we also said, we look at it from a very, very concrete beginning, and then it can go as abstract as possible as it grows.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But we'll kind of divide this into these five components. One is grahas that connects with our astrological horoscope, the five elements, the eight directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The deities, that is the presiding Devatas, and the energetic axis. What does energetic axis mean? So, in the first session, we saw that the sun rises in the east and sets in the west, so that's one energetic or the solar axis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We know Earth's magnetic field, you know, starts in the north and kind of, you know, ends in the south. These are not the right scientific words, but it's from north to south is the Earth's magnetic field. So that's the magnetic axis. And then in Vastu, we have another axis that starts in the northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and then kind of ends in the southwest. We'll see how… how these axes play different roles in our life. So that's the northeast to southwest axis. So these three axes will kind of try to,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Look into, and how it affects us.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What Vastu is not, so it's… this is not the current form of Vastu, where we place some things over here, some things in the east, some things in the northeast, etc, and it kind of changes everything. That's a part of the Jiritha Vastu, the remedies in the part of Jiritha Vastu, but we go more to the core and align it with the Aura stores.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we covered this, Theta Vasu and Jivit Vasu. Theta is that fixed component of the Vasu that you cannot change, probably out of
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, changing houses are difficult, and maybe completely breaking things at the time, making a new WASP layout is not possible, so that's still a component.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the Jeevit component of what you can do on a daily, weekly, monthly, yearly basis to kind of enhance the energy. Like in Shastras, it said that every three years, a Vastu Shanti should be done. We usually do it at the beginning.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And we forget about it. But Shastras speak about doing Mastu Shanti every three years to enhance the auspiciousness in the house. So that's the Jivit component. Or they speak about lighting a Diya outside the main door facing the south that enhances the energies of the main door. So these are the Jivit components that we'll discuss.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And of course, the psychological component, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I usually say that if, you know, everyone in the house is probably having
Dr. Karan Mittal: A particular elemental disturbance, probably everyone is having digestive issues, so we know that digestion is basically fire element, or everyone is having mental health issues, probably depression, anger, et cetera, et cetera. Then somewhere or the other, it's an issue of water and the wind element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, whatever happens in the house, as per traditional Vastu principles, whatever the house is showing you, that will start reflecting in the
Dr. Karan Mittal: People who live in the house, so if the southeast has an issue, it's obvious that people in the house will have issues with digestive system.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we'll have some health issues, we'll have, you know, so we'll come to it. So, so whatever the house shows, what we've discussed, starts reflecting in the inhabitants of the house. That's the Vyashti Vikas principle. Like, if you change
Dr. Karan Mittal: the components around you, it affects you, and vice versa. If you start changing things within, it will also start changing things around you. So that's how both are interlinked to each other.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we also saw these 8 directions, and I'm not repeating, we saw them last time, so these are… there are 4 cardinal directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: North, called as the third.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Salt. Duction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Purva, that is east.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and Pashtim, that is, West. Now, you see, Uttar, the words also signify a lot. The words are not just selected, because there was no other word that's available. Urva means, basically, it's this, it's the, it's the, you know, it's the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Direction where the sun rises and it's also considered good for auspicious beginnings of poor work and you know it comes before everything, okay, similarly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We have 4 cardinal directions which we saw last time, subcardinal directions. Ishanya, that is the, direction between north and east. Agniya, again, the word signifies a lot. Agniya is Agni Tattva, the direction between south and the east. Naivuktir.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is the direction between south and the west, 45 degrees from the south, 45 degrees from the west. It's, Nehrupte, and Vayavya, Vayu, it's the direction between north and the west. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we'll come to it, which direction represents which element. So… so these are the eight directions. We… we'll focus on the eight directions, but as we go into MicroVastu, these directions get further divided and become 16 and 32 also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so depending on how deep you go into the Vastu part, these directions can, you know, keep on, you can keep on dividing every directions further and further.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so what are the directional energies? So let's… I've just picked this up from the Shastras, from Vishwatarma Prakash and all the Shastras. I've not added the modern Vastu component into it, so we'll just stick to the Shastras for this class. So North is basically…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, it has… it's called Uttar, so it has Uttar for, you know, the pursuits of your life, so it's basically the direction of prosperity and happiness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: East, the sun rises in the east, and sun is also a symbol of the health or the longevity. So, and it's also probably the king, as I mentioned. So, east symbolizes vitality, respect, and fame, because I'm king of the planets, right?
Dr. Karan Mittal: South, again, it's for health and longevity, because it's the direction of Yama. We'll come to the DPs later. And West is basically food and animals. Now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Animals, in modern terms, earlier the animals were like, you know, the bulls and the cows and the horses that people own. So probably today's equivalent would be the cars and all the other facilities or luxuries a person can own. So that's the direction for, that's the trait of the West.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Basically, if you remember the word that we use for Northeast, it's Ishanyam. Ish is God, okay? Ishavas, et cetera, the words come from Ish. So Northeast is basically a direction for purity, meditation, spirituality, you know, mental clarity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So everything that, of course, you know, everything that is related to spirituality or to devotion, etc, kind of comes from Northeast. And for spirituality, you need a clear mind. So Northeast also signifies a clear, a stable mind.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, usually, I think the slide comes later, or maybe tomorrow, but… but usually, when we… we schedule a Vasco visit, etc, maybe, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: a week later, or two weeks later, the first thing that we tell the person to kind of start clearing the northeast area of the house. We tell… we guide them to kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: make the layout on phone or the video call, and tell them to start laying the northeast area of the house. Because when the northeast becomes lighter, and there's light that comes in, there's air that's circulating, automatically it starts attracting the auspiciousness and mental clarity that a person needs.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it kind of… if a northeast is very cluttered, or, you know, it's very dark and gloomy, automatically it starts making the mind of the inhabitants, as per the area that northeast is. So, so we try… we tell them to start clearing the northeast to begin with.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we tell them to start clearing the clutter of the house. So that's like you are ready to invite change, energetic change in the house, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: until… until the visit happens, and until the remedies happen, this starts kind of lightening the energy of the house. So that's Northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Southeast Agni, as I said, sorry, the element of Northeast
Dr. Karan Mittal: We'll come to it later, but just for now, it's water element. The southeast is basically fire element, agni and agni. So anything, how do you think about fire as a quality? What are the qualities that you kind of associate with fire?
Dr. Karan Mittal: all these things will be signified, kind of, by Southeast. So, anything that is… that is to do with the energy of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that is to do with the activity, that is to do with the money flow, it is to do with marriage and future generation, because you need, to kind of procreate and all that stuff. So… so that's the… those are the traits of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: fire. Also, from a psychological perspective, enthusiasm in the inhabitants of the house, that aggression to do something, or the willpower to do something. So everything that you associate with fire will kind of be coming from the southeast on.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Southwest is Nairut there. It's earth element. So, what do you… what do you kind of think when you think about earth? So, it's basically the grounding element. It's the element that kind of provides that inertia, it provides that heaviness. So, Southwest is basically…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Signifying all these things and that's why it was said that southwest needs to be the heaviest direction and northeast needs to be the lightest direction because southwest kind of is inertia and earth elements so you kind of reciprocate or you kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: make your house also as for the southwest, as for the Talmud, and you bring in that heaviness. The northeast's water element brings in light, clarity, specialty, so light, lighter compared to the southwest. So that was the axis, we'll come to the axis later, but that's how we think, and that's why
Dr. Karan Mittal: It was said that, you know, sleeping in the southwest is best because it's an, it's an inertia based lunch, it's a tamas one direction, so whoever sleeps there get, get a sound sleep, you know, the sleep is deep because it kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: lowers, you know, it kind of brings in that inertia that's needed for the sound scene. It was also said as the direction of the owner of the house. Why? Because earth element is a stable element, so whoever operates from the earth element becomes stable, and how does the owner need to be? Needs to be stable, commanding.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, needs to have a very stable mind and an approach. So that's what the Southwest is. So the boss of the company, the owner of the house, all these people were said to, kind of, or were instructed to stay in the Southwest.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Northwest is basically YU, or wind. That's why I have here. And now again, you think about the
Dr. Karan Mittal: the… the qualities of the wind. So it's out… it's about, you know, dynam… it's… it's a dynamic direction. It's about flexibility. It's about movement. It's also about mental health, because, because the planet of Northwest is basically moon. So… so… so it's all about
Dr. Karan Mittal: how much of flexibility is there in the house, how much of the people are outgoing in the house, how many social connections they have. If Southwest is corrupted, definitely the mental health will be corrupted. People will not
Dr. Karan Mittal: before talking to other people in the society, in the world, etc. So, it will be like a vicious cycle that will keep on running. So, that's not risk. Now, what do you need to do risk?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Once you know these eight directions and once you've made the layout of the house, start finding what's there in which direction. Where are you sleeping? Which direction are you sleeping? Which direction is the kitchen? So, you know, kitchen is fire element, so is the kitchen somewhere in the southeast or is it in some other direction? The northeast is basically the element of clarity, so what exactly is operating in the northeast of your house?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is it clutter? Is it a storage thing? Have you made it heavy by some other element? Are you putting any other element?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, in Northeast, the element is water, so are you putting fire by making a kitchen over there? Or, or have you instilled, heaviness by kind of making Northeast very heavy?
Dr. Karan Mittal: By putting storage, et cetera, over there. So just being aware of what's lying where in the house will slowly start, you know, kind of showing you what exactly is happening in your lives and in the inhabitants of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We'll come to this chart multiple times later, but this is the basic chart of the Vastu elements. So now, if you see the fire element, basically the southeast direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If you put water over there in form of a toilet or a bathroom, then you are putting an anti-element over there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if there's earth element, you have made it heavy or there's a bedroom, it's fine. So you kind of see what element is there in which direction, if it's southwest or the prithvi element or the nairuta. So nairuta is basically heaviness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And you're putting air, which is the symbol of lightness. So are you putting, you know, are there many open windows, which we discussed in the first session also. That's why it was said that the south and the southwest needs to have less windows, because there are too many windows. It automatically invites the air component into that direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of seeing it from that aspect, and so on. So you kind of see which anti-element is there in which direction. If these elements are there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: in place of these elements. Oh, sorry, you might not be able to see the laser.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, in the directions of the element, if friends or best friends are there, it's still fine. But if enemies are there, then you are kind of putting an anti-element. You'll see this principle in Jyotish also. Every planet has a friend planet, an enemy planet, etc. So, if this is there, then it needs to be remedied.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if these are there, let's still do it. And we'll come to this part, the triangle and the color and the signs later, or in the session 4 or 5.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, these are the five, planets, and, and also, sorry, five elements, and their different properties. So, the three is, again, structure. I'm not repeating it, but just for your reference, so, the three is structure, stability, grounding. One thing is akasha, that is, that is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Expansion and openness, and it was said that the center of your house, the Brahmastan, what we discussed, kind of symbolizes the Akash element, and that's the openness, the element of openness. And that's why it was said that we don't keep anything heavy, or a kiln, or a wall, or a toilet, anything in the center of the house, because it kind of closes that openness element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And there was two. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: three energies that we discussed, so we'll have to now start, kind of, you need to kind of have your layout of your house in front of you, or maybe start referring it to after the class. Solar is, again, from east to west, that's the
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's the movement of the sun, okay, and that's how it is ideally also. So east symbolizes health, et cetera, and west is again what we saw, food and animals. Magnet is
Dr. Karan Mittal: north to south, and cosmic is from northeast to southwest. That's the pranic flow. That depends on the principles of the DTs of the Vastu, which we'll see as we go into the DTs part. So these are the three different axes that operate into your house, and we…
Dr. Karan Mittal: In Vastu, these axes play a very important role. So now, we try to align our sleeping directions as per the, movement of the sun. So we usually say that the head should be in the east, or should be in the south while sleeping, because when the head is in the east, at least you're aligning your sun to the solar axis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: When it's in the south, you're trying to align yourself with the magnetic axis. Our head, as per Vasu principles, or Jyotish principles, is basically the north pole, and the legs are the south pole. If you keep your head in the north direction, and so it's like north and north.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, and we know that from the principles of magnetism that both tell each other, so that's why we slip and sleep with our head in the south, which is
Dr. Karan Mittal: north in the south, and our legs, which is the south pole of our body, in the north. So, we align our bodies as per the cardinal directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, that's what. So, as we go ahead, you'll start seeing that
Dr. Karan Mittal: the chart, or in fact, if you go deeper into Astro Vastu, the chart also can pinpoint to the problems in the Vastu, and vice versa. Like, if a person
Dr. Karan Mittal: has studied both deep enough, both the links can be known. So, Saturn, what we… Abhuji mentioned also, it's not just something in your horoscope, there's a… there's a Vastu component to it also, there's a historical component to it also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the attributes of Saturn are not just seen in the chart, it can also show up in the basket.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Or, or any of these planets, okay? So I had mentioned in the first class also that if your Guru Desha is on, Guru is the planet of the northeast direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and your northeast is again clogged up, or is kind of cluttered, or there's no light, there's humidity, you know, it's like probably the closed room of your house. Automatically, your inner guru is aligned.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the universal guru in the sense your chart is aligned, but the middle component, or the component that connects both, your vastu, is showing a weak guru, so that guru darsha will not give you as much benefits as it could give you with a properly aligned northeast direction. So that's why
Dr. Karan Mittal: I usually say that, clear up the Northeast, because automatically it brings in the auspiciousness of Jupiter planet into the house, and Jupiter, as we know, stands for many auspicious things, right, from spirituality to money, and many more such things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So how do we start, you know, kind of going deeper? Since today we read about the five elements, you usually start seeing how are these elements reflecting in my life or the life of the people who live in the same comms. So if Earth, I'll not read the whole chart, I'll just share it on the group for you to refer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if the earth element is balanced, or your southwest is balanced, automatically the people in the house have stable thought flow, they have consistency, they have, you know, they have the authority that they want in their business, in their workplace.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you… they have stability in different aspects of life, whether it's finances, whether it's mental thoughts, whether it's bodily stability, like, not… not falling ill too much, okay? So, that's a… that's a sign of stable or balanced Earth element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But, of course, if Southwest is imbalanced, whether it's in access or it's deficient.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then automatically those signs of excess of worth element like heaviness, lethargy, stagnation, obesity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Diseases related to the earth element like diabetes, et cetera, what I am in accordance to from the Pancha Mahabhuta perspective, these things will start showing up or things being stuck at workplace, et cetera. So that's outburst. And if it's deficient, then you're not racing thoughts, instability.
Dr. Karan Mittal: weak boundaries, feeling unsafe. So, these things will start showing, of course, not fully, but you will see a pattern, and, you know, in the different inhabitants of the house, you'll start seeing this
Dr. Karan Mittal: this pattern that, okay, this earth element pattern is showing up. So a good exercise for today or tomorrow morning would be to kind of start seeing what are the patterns that you're seeing in your house. What are the areas that your house probably has
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the elements of which, which particular component of, of your house, like bedroom, toilets, kitchen are in which directions. So just kind of starting to map.
Dr. Karan Mittal: These things will try to give you an idea. Probably out of 5 members, 3 might show earth element, 2 might not show earth element issues. That's fine, but that will also point that something in the southwest needs to work. Okay, something in the southwest needs to be announced and so on. So I'll just share this chart instead of reading the whole chart.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, of course, there are doubts. We can we can discuss it tomorrow on WhatsApp. But these are the different elements and how they show up if there are vasculosis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we kind of identify the imbalance. We start with kind of first making the layout, Then, finding which
Dr. Karan Mittal: component of the house is in which direction and which element? Is there any anti-element? And then, if you want to go a bit deeper, then you go deeper and start seeing the patterns.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of what's reflecting in the members of the family who are staying in the same house, so it will start giving you the Jivit component of the Vastu, and how to rectify it, we'll see eventually in the next 2 sessions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now, every session, maybe the next two sessions, we'll also see a few components that Shastras or that Arvastu Rishis have prescribed for the Jeevat.
Dr. Karan Mittal: part, so that enhances the energies of your house. First thing we… we just saw, that over the weekend, clear the northeast. First thing is we clear the northeast. If… if needed, later on, put some… some fragrant thing, et cetera, in the northeast to clear the energy, but first declutter the northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: bring in light, bring in air, bring in, bring in, bring in some clarity into the Northeast by putting a bulb, or tube light, etc, and clear the Northeast. Then, if you want to enhance it, definitely some fragrance, some DIY, etc, could also work, but for now, clear the Northeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Second.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is the salt, usage of salt. Now, salt, basically, from the energetic principles, energetic master principles, it's considered to be a master energy cleanser. Of course, there are other things also, different essential oils, different,
Dr. Karan Mittal: herbs, et cetera, that are also effective, but salt is easily available, cheap, and can be done on a regular basis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Usually, we're…
Dr. Karan Mittal: The traditional people in Vastu, irrespective of wherever is the toilet in the house, they prescribe keeping a bowl of salt in the toilets to kind of keep on absorbing that negativity because as for original Vastu, as for Vedic Vastu, toilets were never meant to be inside the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: They were meant to be outside the village, somewhere far away. So, so, so… just…
Dr. Karan Mittal: And because nowadays we live in the flat system among the system, the toilets are there inside the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: as… because we don't have option, keeping a solid bowl definitely helps, kind of, absorbing those negative energies, and change it every few days, whenever it becomes watery. In rainy season, it happens quite frequently, but then every fortnight is warranted.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What we do is, once a month is, we sprinkle some
Dr. Karan Mittal: Salt on the floor in the evenings like after around sunset and like just before sunset because we need to broom that salt and after keeping it for 15 to 20 minutes we just
Dr. Karan Mittal: With a broom, we kind of clear that, salt, and then flush it in the, in the WC. So that also, whatever
Dr. Karan Mittal: It absorbs the negative energies of the space and kind of makes the room lighter. If that's not possible, then in the daily more.
Dr. Karan Mittal: putting some amount of salt, but it makes the flow sticky. So, depending on your, convenience, you can do this exercise once a month, at least. And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Again, coming to the Jiva component or yourself component, many energy modalities like reiki, prani, healing, et cetera, prescribe taking salt bath. So putting a feast full of salt in your bathing water.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then kind of, you know, with the mug, just putting the salt from head to toe, letting it stay on the body for a few minutes, like 1 or 2 minutes, and then taking a normal bath also clears up your chakras in your auric field. So people who interact with too many people, are into these healing professions, who are sick often.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Who have too much of interaction and ground, etc. These things kind of keep… or if your house also has many people visiting it, for social reasons or for, professional reasons, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: soil kind of does a lot of cleansing that's needed for the house. Earlier, we did it in the form of Dhu, Mughal, Kinshasas, or the Sphin. Those things were also done. That is also
Dr. Karan Mittal: Completely fine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And maybe the second component for today is the Mahadwa, or the main entrance. So in Vasu, the Mahadwa, in fact, in the first session, I'd said that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Lot of importance is given to the Mahadwa, or the main entrance part in the Vastu.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Right from how it is placed, the direction of the door, to how the door opens, like, clockwise, anti-clockwise, to how the door is decorated, what are the different components on the door, all these things played a very important role in Maslow.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And of course, from a neuro architecture perspective, a main doors is, you know, it kind of signifies a threshold, a threshold between or a boundary between the external world and the and your private personal world. So having a good main door or a enhanced main door.
Dr. Karan Mittal: whenever you step inside the window, it automatically instills that boundary, that positivity, it automatically switches off your psychological stress, etc, because now you know that you're entering into a different space. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, in Vastu, usually it was said that the main door always should be brightly lit.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course.
Dr. Karan Mittal: During the daytime, at least, so there shouldn't be any shadow, etc. It shouldn't be dark, gloomy, the area around the main door. It should be fragrant enough, so lighting, something, like a roof, or a diffuser, or keeping some, some deodorizer, or some, some essential oil component.
Dr. Karan Mittal: anything that kind of keeps the main door area fragrant enough, lit enough, had a lot of importance, because it attracted the positivity into the house. Also, probably putting some
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oren, or some, some, something that
Dr. Karan Mittal: makes the main node look aesthetic, and then kind of, you know, like, you just start feeling happy or contented while looking at the main node. So all these things were given importance, and that's why making it a really
Dr. Karan Mittal: putting Devdas, putting a Dhoop, putting a Diyar in the evening at the main moon, etc, signified all these things, because it enhanced the positivity that came into the house, and also blocked
Dr. Karan Mittal: anything negative coming into the house. So, so, so that was the main door, and, and what I would recommend is, like, like, putting a torah in, or cleaning the main door on a regular basis, putting, putting nowadays we have those,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Camper, phone, etc. So, something on the main node that kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: starts inviting that auspiciousness in the house is a good step to start working on the Jiva Crossroads. So, one is clearing the northeast, soil cleanse, and the third thing that we discussed for Jiva Crossroads is the Mahadwar entrance, or how to work on the entrance of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what do we do before the next session is identifying
Dr. Karan Mittal: what component lies in which direction of the house, seeing if there is an anti-element. I'll share the chart after the session on the app.
Dr. Karan Mittal: make the layout of the house, find the layout of the house, find the Burma sign, take the directions, make the gr
Dr. Karan Mittal: And of course, noting if you're not done it yet, then noting the Rashi Swami, Levna Swami, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: For for reference coming tomorrow's session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, you can stop here and take questions.
GOVINDA Das: Cutter.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Raj.
GOVINDA Das: According to what you explained about all the directions in the home.
GOVINDA Das: You know, if people already have something on the northeast.
GOVINDA Das: Which is impossible to move at this stage.
GOVINDA Das: You know, that might cause panic to them already. My God, you know.
GOVINDA Das: There is so much of lot, so what is the immediate… Solution, because…
GOVINDA Das: You know, in the cities, in the building.
GOVINDA Das: You know, if there is a… if there is something which is not very auspicious in the Northeast.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than panicking, what's… what is the severity they have to follow?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, thank you, Prabhuji. So, so yeah, definitely, Prabh
Dr. Karan Mittal: Firstly, of course, as we go ahead, we'll discuss what could be done for a toilet or a kitchen in the Northeast, that will happen. But to begin with, of course, keeping whatever area is available to you. Suppose there's a toilet
Dr. Karan Mittal: But the area that is outside the toilet, at least keeping that area clean, keeping the toilet clean enough, okay, on a regular basis, so that the negative energy doesn't accumulate. Keeping the salt bowl in the toilet will also enhance,
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, we'll kind of keep that negative energy of the toilet in the northeast constructed. If it's a kitchen, that's a fire element, then again, keeping kitchen dry, clean, you know, cleaning the cupboards, etc, on a regular basis, so that
Dr. Karan Mittal: the negativity does not accumulate in the northeast direction, so whatever area is available. Full northeast probably is not covered with toilet or kitchen, but whatever area is available to you, just working on that area, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of limiting the negative component of whatever thing is there in the northeast to begin with, that will start working. There's nothing to panic, basically. We work around it. So as we go ahead, we'll of course discuss how to kind of rectify these things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Should I take questions? Yeah, Shubhamji.
Shubham K: It was a related question here, so what do you do with that ball of salt after a fortnight, or a week?
Dr. Karan Mittal: You put it in the WCN, flash it.
Shubham K: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any salt that is used for cleansing is usually flushed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Focus.
NAman Kashyap: Hi, Krish.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
NAman Kashyap: I have one question. I mean, there are small, small, questions which I'll ask. One, like, you know, philosophical question is, with the same Vastu, there are different people in the home who are living.
NAman Kashyap: and then different people are affected differently. If there is any Vaishtadorsh, that might not come to everyone. It might come to only one person like that. So, can you please elaborate what might be the reason for that? Is it because of their charts?
NAman Kashyap: Or what? So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, it's because of charts, and that's where combining astrology and Vasu comes into picture. It's like, if you have a debilitated
Dr. Karan Mittal: Jupiter, or a malefic Jupiter in your chart, and also the northeast of your house is problematic, it will start showing more results to that particular… more negative results to that person.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But suppose you have a good Jupiter, a very good Jupiter, but still your northeast is, you know, it's like one plus one, one minus one, and it's like, just do some, you just need to do some mathematics. But if you have a very good Jupiter and a very good northeast corner of the house, the whole effect will become one plus one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so it's like… that's how it works. Like, in the same building also, you'll see
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, like, the same series of flat, everyone having different fits. This is how it works. It's called astrovascular control, yeah.
NAman Kashyap: So, I mean, so when selecting a new home or changes, then we can, I mean, like, I cannot think about all the members, I mean, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Owner of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We see the owner of the house, we get the lines, and also we see the house shouldn't have any Maha Dosha, like, the major 3-4 Dosha that I mentioned. That does the work. And then selecting the room as per their house, all these micro-components.
NAman Kashyap: Okay, so main thing is, owner of the home, his Estro Vastu should be mapped.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I didn.
NAman Kashyap: At least that, yeah, and not the Mahadarshas. Okay.
NAman Kashyap: And, probably then, just, just a thing that, so you mentioned about the, Lord and the Deity. So again, just a follow-up question is, so Lord are, Lord is out of the nine planets, and the Deity is the Devata.
NAman Kashyap: Yes. Of that. Okay, because I got confused, because Vaispati also, in a sense, is a Devta, Buddha is also a Devta, so that… there was a confusion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, but this goes more to the Vedic realm. In Vedic realm, these are very separate components. Like Chandra becomes a Deva, but Soma is a Vedic Devata. So the names in Puranic tradition are the same. Like Soma becomes Chandra's Equivalent. So it goes very Vedic, like you have to trace it to the Vedic realm.
NAman Kashyap: Okay. And a little confusion about Gochar and the Vimsoteri Dasha. So, basically, what I understood is, like, at the birth, say, for me, it was the Jupiter Mahadasha.
NAman Kashyap: for some years, and then after that, Saturn, and it's moving. So then, what is Gotcha? Gotcha is one planet moving, like Purji was mentioning.
NAman Kashyap: Saturn moving to different, different places, so I'm a little confused.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I've lost Nomenji, I guess. Oh.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so, yeah, so, yeah, so, dashas are basically, Prabhuji will also add to it, but dashas are basically, that's what you mentioned, as per the nakshatra, that's a fixed cycle. Once you're born in a Pravalya Murakshira nakshatra, it's the Mangal, and the cycle for 120 years is fixed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Bhojara is when you bring out your Lagna Koli, okay, what is the placement of today? Like, Shani today is placed in Meen Rashi, so if I have a Meen
Dr. Karan Mittal: So my Shani is placed in my Lagna right now. Okay, so it's current, like your Lagna Kunali is your photograph of your birth. It is imposing current position of the universe or the solar system onto that photograph. It's like what's happening right now in the solar system. You're placing those planets in your Lagna Kunali. That's Rocha.
NAman Kashyap: So, Gochar changes every day. I mean, like, it changes constantly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, yeah. So, every planet, every… it depends, like, moon will change every two and a half days.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Saturn will change every two and a half years. So, in your same chart, the Moon will change very quickly. Saturn will take 30 years to make a circle. Jupiter will take 12 years to make a circle. So, it keeps on changing.
NAman Kashyap: So, Prabhuji, but, so, I mean, like, we discussed that we can take the indication when the Dasha, so, like, he's the actor, and Dasha is the, you know, the
NAman Kashyap: at that point, what role he's playing. When Dasha changes, the life, you know, the different things changes. In Venus, it is a different thing. In Saturn, it is a different thing.
NAman Kashyap: So, till that time, I… I could understand, okay, if I have to take some decisions, I can check my dasha. But now, if gochar is also there, then combining the dasha also and the gochar also, if I want to take some decisions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It depends on how micro level you want to go, like month level, day level, week level. There's something called a Sarotha Bhatta, which predicts in hours, next few hours, what will happen. So it's like, it's like a macro system is Dasha, and then Gochar also takes it to more micro levels. Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But with Coachella, I think… Do that, yeah.
NAman Kashyap: This one.
GOVINDA Das: See, again, therefore, you know, you will… if you get into… Precision of that…
GOVINDA Das: Then you'll not function only. That is the science which the Rishis have given.
GOVINDA Das: So it's like, you know, appropriately, you know, that is what you have to focus on because the Purushartha is always much greater than the influence.
GOVINDA Das: You know, having that Purushartha mindset.
GOVINDA Das: Using the astrology, not being obsessed with it.
GOVINDA Das: You know, and therefore, if you study in the Shastra also.
GOVINDA Das: The Jyotish Shastrakiya to Parikshit Maharaj
GOVINDA Das: Description, you give a certain description.
GOVINDA Das: Lord Chaitanya also, certain description they did not give about he taking sannyas.
GOVINDA Das: Right, so therefore it is not so important to get into extremely precise. It is not that you are sending rocket to the moon.
GOVINDA Das: You know, basic understanding is important so that you can experience adventure in life.
GOVINDA Das: No.
NAman Kashyap: Okay, brill.
GOVINDA Das: Any other question or comments? Yeah, Shubham.
GOVINDA Das: Nice.
Shubham K: Prabhuji, yes, Prabhuji. Hi, Krishna. So, I had a related question here. So, I had asked the question to Dr. Karan also, but wanted to know your perspective. So, like, for certain things, how do we know that how much should we endeavor? Because we can just keep endeavoring and
Shubham K: We cannot quantitatively say from chat that this is how much wealth you will get, or how much progress you can make in any field.
GOVINDA Das: Endeavor is, endeavor is endless, but endeavoring on a particular, if you have a destination, oh, I want to have, I want to have this particular amount of money that is not.
GOVINDA Das: good. To have wealth is good, but to want to have wealth specifically this much is not correct.
GOVINDA Das: you know, that doesn't… therefore, I think I mentioned this… I don't know if I remember here… the…
GOVINDA Das: Devi Shetty, the mayor, one of the famous
GOVINDA Das: Doctor, he mentioned that even the footballers
GOVINDA Das: You know, it is known that the professional footballers, they have almost like the present about 460 people have cardiac arrest.
GOVINDA Das: Recorded. It's not only those who are playing international games. Even they have a cardiac arrest.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: So… so therefore, when the… when you make anything mechanical.
GOVINDA Das: No, put more pressure, put more pressure. Therefore, even in the sports field, sport is supposed to remove your anxiety, not increase your anxiety.
GOVINDA Das: When sport is played only to win, it loses the entire connotation of sports.
GOVINDA Das: Sports is not there to win or lose. Sports is there to feel excitement, happiness.
GOVINDA Das: Right? But now what has happened? Sport has become cause of anxiety.
GOVINDA Das: So similarly, when you become specifically focused on, I want to endeavor on this, I want to be educated. Now, if you don't become a doctor, you can be something else. You can't become an engineer, you can be something else. But when that focus is only, I will be engineer at any cost, that means your life will go away.
GOVINDA Das: We'll spend 5, 7, 8 years. I want to be an IS officer only.
GOVINDA Das: No, when that stubbornness does not constitute endeavor.
GOVINDA Das: That considered as stubbornness only, not prayas.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, hot. It is hot, not determination.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So, therefore, astrology Does not tell your destiny and your endeavor should be.
GOVINDA Das: Focused on the action.
GOVINDA Das: With the help of astrology, work properly, get guidance, and move forward.
GOVINDA Das: No, I know some students who did not get an Ames Medical.
GOVINDA Das: They said, unless I'll get in AIMS, I will keep trying.
GOVINDA Das: you know. Now, can you call it a determination?
GOVINDA Das: No, that is sometime… not sometime. Most of the time it falls into the category of Stubbornness.
GOVINDA Das: So one has to be careful about that.
Shubham K: So then it becomes very personal that when, what balance to keep, right? Like how much to endeavor and what, how much not like in a, some guidance.
iPhone: We'll see about it.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, what you said, last one?
Shubham K: Like, then, then it will need, very personal guidance, right? When to stop and…
GOVINDA Das: That personal guidance is required and personal, you know, common sense also. When we become obsessed with something, our common sense is lost.
GOVINDA Das: Or then you should be willing to say, you know, in certain position, there are people who have the, I remember when I was learning, our teacher was telling that some people, they have the conflicting mind chart, either Bhikkhari or Firadhikari.
GOVINDA Das: You know, it's, it's like when you become a soldier, either you come back alive or you die.
GOVINDA Das: You know, fighting the battle. So just see the contradiction between the two. Either it is death or it is victory.
GOVINDA Das: You know, if we can, if people can handle that, that's okay, but if they cannot handle, then there has to be something.
GOVINDA Das: You know, balancing between the, in the contradictory activities.
GOVINDA Das: If not this one, I can do this one. If not this one, I can do this one. Like that.
Shubham K: Professor, one last question. So, I had heard your… one of your lectures where you were quoting Bhagavad Gita, probably didn't understand it completely. So, there you're saying that the way material works is very impos… In a very impersonal way, and Krishna doesn't directly interfere.
Shubham K: So, I just had a question then, what will be the place of remedies, or what will be the place of prayers to, let's say, Lord Krishna himself?
GOVINDA Das: No.
GOVINDA Das: See, again, there are two principles. One is the laws of
GOVINDA Das: Laws of nature and the grace of God, they should be integrated together. We focus too much on grace.
GOVINDA Das: And not focus on the law and sometimes we focus too much on the laws and not on the grace of God when you give up grace of God.
GOVINDA Das: The human endeavor has a limitation.
GOVINDA Das: Or you only focus on grace of God, then you minimize human endeavor.
GOVINDA Das: Defer tasma sereweshu kaleishu mamanusmara y
GOVINDA Das: You know, the smaran, therefore, the ramayana of Valmiki Maharshi is centered around endeavor.
GOVINDA Das: The Ramayana of Tulsidas is centered around grace.
GOVINDA Das: No, the, the concept of Lord Ram being Bhagavan.
GOVINDA Das: Is repeatedly brought in.
GOVINDA Das: pulsi manas.
GOVINDA Das: You know, there is a historical background also, but in Valmiki's Ramayan, there is a Purushartha, there is an ende
GOVINDA Das: It doesn't matter from home.
GOVINDA Das: So when you harmonize this, And then also Krishna says that.
GOVINDA Das: You know, 18.66, or in the 12th chapter, it says, you know, those who take my shelter, I swiftly deliver them from the nations. So it's a harmony between the two.
GOVINDA Das: Purshartha and Pratana, Dona Bhih Yeah, one last 2 questions we'll take. Now, Vijit and Mah.
Mahesh Wagh: Yes.
Mahesh Wagh: Probably you mentioned about, Sadi Sati, right? And where, certain culture is there in, Chhattisgarh, Kundalini. Yeah. For, 7… 7 years, 7.5 years.
GOVINDA Das: 7 and a half years, yeah.
Mahesh Wagh: Yeah, so how that placement is there, Rajiv, from, like, when, from Lucknow, that is there, you mentioned about moon, right? So when that placement happens, and is it sequential, or it is, like, periodically happens, that's 2.5, 2.5 years.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
Mahesh Wagh: Second part.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, we'll complete the first one.
Mahesh Wagh: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: You know, we can show you the chart tomorrow, you know, to understand this.
GOVINDA Das: You know, that it happens every 30 years. No, every, 22 and a half years.
Mahesh Wagh: Okay, in that also, I wanted to understand the… there is 2.5U, then 2.5U, and then 2.5, or it is, like, in between, that there's a gap.
GOVINDA Das: No, there is no, unless in the first phase of your Sade Sati, if Shani becomes retro.
GOVINDA Das: For 1 or 2 months, he goes back in his previous house.
GOVINDA Das: But that is, you know, not a common thing, because they'll come back again to the same house.
GOVINDA Das: And the sadhisati continues. So it is two and a half years first house.
GOVINDA Das: One house away from moon, that is first phase of Sadhisati, with the moon is the second phase of Sadhisati, and away from the moon is the third phase of Sadhisati.
Mahesh Wagh: Oh, that's clear. Now, Dr. Karanji, he mentioned about a lot of remedies, right? He was specifically mentioning about three things, yatni, dhanatapa, and additionally, you know, many astrologers, they will tell about mantras, mantras remedy also, or some stone-related things. So, Prabhuji, how much allocation, you know.
Mahesh Wagh: we are supposed to do in this area as part of… because for home procedure, a lot of remedies, right, today, we should do this to eradicate that. But in order for
Mahesh Wagh: to Saadi Saadi perspective, what are the allocation? Not Saadi Saadi, but in general, also, if any planet is getting malefic, so what are the allocation in terms of these, components.
GOVINDA Das: Again, these are all, you know, depending upon resources, people spend, make more, it's like, you know, if you have a
GOVINDA Das: House leaking, you can keep a bucket also, or you can put a plastic also, or you can, next time when the rain stopped, you can put a new floor also, right?
GOVINDA Das: So depending on what are the resources available, people feel one of the most important mindset of the remedial measures is it gives some kind of good feeling in the first place.
GOVINDA Das: Like in the Bhakti Rasamarasundaram Goswami expl
GOVINDA Das: The principle of karma is that
GOVINDA Das: In the rare cases, it completely removes.
GOVINDA Das: In some cases, it minimizes.
GOVINDA Das: In most of the cases, it enhances our mindset itself.
GOVINDA Das: So, remedials are also like that. It enhances our mindset.
GOVINDA Das: It minimizes our karma.
GOVINDA Das: But rarely, it completely destroys our karma.
GOVINDA Das: Like, for example, if you're… if you're 2nd and 3rd house.
GOVINDA Das: Are not connected for a pleasant voice.
GOVINDA Das: A singer's voice.
GOVINDA Das: Right, however much remedy you do without going for learning music.
GOVINDA Das: Right. It is not going to change your throat. You may learn the art of singing, but that does not change.
GOVINDA Das: The… the voice box, which has come from the… the
GOVINDA Das: the karmic cycle. So, therefore, understand the remedies are there.
GOVINDA Das: For enhancing our perspective, remedies are there to minimize the impact itself. Remedies are there in some cases to completely remove.
GOVINDA Das: But we can begin, we can begin with the changing of the perspective.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than having that determination or stubbornness, I want to change my karma completely. You know, that is not possible all the time.
GOVINDA Das: Karan, do you want to add something on this.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We'll take.
GOVINDA Das: Last question.
GOVINDA Das: Abhijit, you asked.
Mahesh Wagh: Thank you, Bhoji. That.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you.
GOVINDA Das: We'll up. Okay.
NAman Kashyap: Did you… Which is even not able to hear you.
NAman Kashyap: Roger, he's speaking something.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you.
NAman Kashyap: Puri, just a small question, Puri. So, Puri, you mentioned about Gotra Rishi, Govind Puri. So, I mean, connecting to that, can you elaborate that a little? I mean, what.
GOVINDA Das: Tomorrow we are doing that, you know, when we are discussing the, you know, the entire Bhagavatam Vibh Cant
GOVINDA Das: Okay. From the astrological, how the planet influence.
GOVINDA Das: We'll take that. Okay.
NAman Kashyap: And you mentioned 22 and a half years.
Prasath Kumar R: Only.
NAman Kashyap: After that, it will come again.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, that's when the shani is rotating, no? You know, it goes off.
GOVINDA Das: Sending me.
NAman Kashyap: Oh.
GOVINDA Das: 30. Shani takes 30 years to go around.
GOVINDA Das: Two and a half years, two and a half years, two and a half years, you know, 12 zodiacs ends up there. Should take 30 years.
GOVINDA Das: Again, it's not… it's nothing to worry, that's what we're discussing.
NAman Kashyap: Yeah, yeah. I mean, the learnings. I mean, we have. So there would be some learnings which are not complete in the first Saraswati. So we'll have to do that.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you. So I'll stop here and meet tomorrow again.
NAman Kashyap: Thank you. Thank you, Camdi.
NAman Kashyap: election.
Sattvastha Ventures: Thank you, everybody.
NAman Kashyap: I think it'.